Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - to The President of Congress., 1781 April 24; A.L.S. 6p.; Laurens, John. Paris
    Relative to the method of conveying the borrowed money to America. Made arrangements whereby the "Indian," sold by the Chevalier de Luxemb[o]urg to the State of South Carolina for three years, should convey the money to America. Apprehends an unfavorable reply to the request that the military effects from the public arsenals should be obtained on credit. Encloses a copy of the military stores, No. 2, that can be obtained in the maritime places from the War Department. Difficulty in obtaining the howitzers and the trouble encountered in transporting shells from the interior of the Kingdom. Will proceed to Brest as soon as he accomplishes everything that requires his presence here, to hasten the departure of the frigate. Will, in the meanwhile, detail Capt. [William] Jackson, who accompanied him from America, to exert his utmost effort to get the "Indian" to sea without loss of time.
  - to John Laurens., 1781 April 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    Has a new ship of twenty guns, ready to put to sea by the 5th of June. Desires any freight he has to send. Asks him to forward his letters and despatches in time to go by her.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 April 29; D.S. 1p.; Greive, George. Passy
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 April 29; D.S. 1p.; Henzile, Charles. Passy
  - to John Laurens., 1781 May 29; L.S. 2p.; Schweighauser, John D. Nantes
    Articles he received and loaded on board the "Active," Capt. Barnes, consigned to the Board of War, Philadelphia.
  - to Lord [Cornwallis?]., 1781 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Tarleton, Banastre. Col. Adams's Plantation
    Thinks la Fayette passed the South Anna or Pamunky for the mountain road at Bird's ordinary. Left the Three Notched Road for the benefit of forage and to communicate with him. Shall strike it again tomorrow and go by Napier's to Pier's Mill. La Fayette's design is to follow.
  - to Louis XVI., 1781 June 13; D.S. Sam[uel] Huntington, President, and sealed. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Letter to the King of France expressing the strongest sentiments of gratitude for the measures adopted by His Majesty to render the cause of the United States triumphant.
  - to James Moylan., 1781 June 23; L. 2p.; Galatheau, Captain de. L'Orient
    The capture of his ship, "Marquis de la Fayette," by three English war vessels while on his voyage to America. Set sail with the frigate "Alliance" as a convoy. Took two English privateers the first few days out. Became separated and lost sight of the "Alliance," during a violent storm. Was pursued by three English warships. Engaged in battle with one of them, the "Endymion," of forty-eight guns. After a combat at close quarters lasting over three hours was obliged to yield to superior force. Was hampered by a small crew, had sixty sick persons on board and had ninety English prisoners to restrain. His casualties were twenty killed or wounded, and his vessel was so badly battered that it had to be towed for twelve days by the English warship. The two other English vessels were standing by when he surrendered.
    (In French. Press copy.)
  - to Jean Holker. Paris., 1781 June 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Behic, -----. Canteleu
    Seeks the appointment of his cousin, Galart des Graux, as Consul at Bayonne.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 June 26; D. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution approving of John Barry's conduct in releasing the ship belonging to the subjects of the Republic of Venice.
  - to Messrs. J. Rocquette, J. A. Else(voi)[rie]r and Brothers Rocquette, Rotterdam., 1781 June 27; L. 2p.; -----, -----
    Their bay continues in the same situation. Impossible to say whether a change may happen by the superiority of the French fleet this summer. The British make most rapid strides in Virginia and continue to destroy all tobacco in the public warehouses.
    (Duplicate.)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 July 2; D.S. 2p.; The Admiralty office at Dunkirk
    An extract from the records giving a declaration made by several French sailors who had formed part of the crew of the privateer 'La Revanche," Capt. Gustavus Conyngham, respecting their rights to share in the prizes taken by the latter vessel.
  - to Jean Holker, 1781 July 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Behic, -----. Canteleu
    Fears the vessel is lost which was bringing the newly appointed Consul-General to France. Thinks it better to have Frenchmen of good family as Consuls in the French ports; foreigners in that position would meet with slight consideration.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 July 8; D.S. 1p.; Folger, Timothy. Passy
  - to [Armand-Thomas Hue de] Miromesnil., 1781 July 10; L. 1p.; Oudet, -----
    Sends a quatrain composed on the spur of the moment by M. [Aimé Ambroise Joseph] Feutry on hearing M. Miromesnil's name mentioned. pays a tribute to the latter's efforts and influence in the interest of French literature. Reply of M. Miromesnil thanking M. Oudet and I. Feutry. Hopes he will soon see false philosophy banished and human knowledge increase.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 July 11; 5p.; The Pennsylvania Gazette
    Account of engagements with the enemy at Augusta, Georgia, and near Williamsburg, Virginia. Taken chiefly from letters from Marquis de la Fayette to Samuel Huntington and to General [Nathanael] Greene.
  - to Mr. Elka[nah] Watson., 1781 July 17; L.S. 1p.; Benson, George. Boston
    The second bills of exchange on France intercepted. Requests him to write to the Commissioner at Paris to stop payment.
  - to J. Robinson, Commanding the "Pilgrim," Privateer, Brest., 1781 August 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, Edward Tye. London
    In reference to the exchange of Captain Cathcart, Commander of the "Essex," privateer, and crew.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 August 21; D. 3p.; Memorandum
    Account of the public chastisement of Maria de los Dolores Lopez, a native of Seville, on above date, covicted of having been in league with the Devil.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 September 12; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Ordering a balance of 42,189 livres to be paid to W[illiam] Lee.
    Printed in Journals of Congress, Philadelphia, 1781, VII, 187.
  - to Col. Hugh Shields, Philadelphia., 1781 September 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Butler, A. Williamsburg Virginia
    Thirty-seven ships of war ride triumphant in their [Chesapeake] Bay. The Comte de Grasse says he will stay until [Lord] Cornwallis is reduced. Greatest harmony subsists between the French and American Supplies beginning to flow in; everything promises success. The who army holds a position within three quarters of a mile from York, in full view of the enemy. Latest accounts from the south; action between Gen. [Alexander] Stuart and Gen. [Nathanael] Greene; the British repulsed; Col. [William] Washington's regiment cut to pieces. Mentions names of wounded officers. Introducing the bearer, Captain James O'Hara.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 September 27; Folio. Pp. 2, 8, 56. Printed.; Sales Catalogue of the "Marquis de la Fayette."
    The "Marquis de la Fayette," a French prize, taken on her passage to Boston by His Majesty's ships of war "Endymion," "Egmont," "Suffolk," "Grafton," "Trident" and "Bristol." To be sold by the Candle at Garraway's Coffee-House, in Exchange Alley, Cornhill, [London], on September 27, October 11, 1781, and January 29, 30, 31, February 5, 6, 7, 1782. [With Ms. marginal notes by Jonathan Williams, Jr.]
  - to John Jay., 1781 September 30; L.S. 7p.; Gillon, Alexander. Corunna
    Defends himself against the charges made by Major [William] Jackson.
  - to [David Salisbury] Franks., 1781 October 2; A.L.S. 8p.; Harrison, Richard. Cadiz
    Tells him not to give himself further uneasiness on the score of his shipper and his colleagues. Business relations.
  - to The Society Amore Patriae., 1781 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning the editing and translating of their book, Considerations; regrets the necessity for secrecy on the part of such a Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781; A.L.S. 2p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Has been engraver and printer to the King of Portugal; desires work.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 October 15; A. Poem. 3p.; Thibouzet, -----. Paris
    On the struggle for independence in America. A tribute to Dr. Franklin and King Louis of France.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 October 19; D.S. [Charles, Earl] Cornwallis and Thomas Symonds. 9p.; Articles of Capitulation. Yorktown, Virginia
    Showing in parallel columns the terms asked by the British, and the terms granted, amended or refused by the allied French and Americans.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 November 7 to 1782 February 27; Mem. 1p.; List of Notes Accepted by John Adams
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 November 17 to December 21; Mem. S. 2p.; Barry, Captain John
    Account with crew.
  - to C.W.F. Dumas., 1781 November 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Asking for a continuation of his interesting letters, which in future will pass through the office of Foreign Affairs; regretting the inability of Congress to raise his salary for the present.
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.], Nantes., 1781 November 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Limozin, Andrew. Havre
    Congratulates him on the good news received at Brest, of the surrender of [Lord] Cornwallis. Asks him to procure the release, through Dr. Franklin, of the Captain and Lieutenant of an American privateer sloop in prison at Havre.
  - to Mlle. -----., 1781 November 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Gastellier, René-Georges. Montargis
    Begging her to present two of his works to Dr. Franklin, as a feeble token of his regard and veneration. In commemoration of the brilliant victory at York and the way the regiment of Gâtinais distinguished itself, desires Dr. Franklin to accord him a membership in the [American] Philosophical Society at Philadelphia, of which he is President.
  - to John de Neufville and Son., 1781 December 3; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Has no authority to interfere in the direction of the Continental goods which Mr. [Alexander] Gillon contracted to convey to America, but such as is derived from the desire of Dr. Franklin to take the best care of them in his power. Dr. Franklin's opinion of their not permitting Mr. Gillon to convey the goods to America. The damages the owners claim, to be stated and if they are such as cannot be agreed to, he is ready to arbitrate. According to another desire of Dr. Franklin, he offers to sell all the goods to Messrs. de Neufville and asks on what terms they will take them. Thinks this plan would settle all disputes at once.
  - to Jonathan Williams, Jr., 1781 December 4; Limozin, Andrew. Havre
    Request to recommend him to Dr. Franklin for the appointment as Consul for the United States at Havre.
  - to John Adams., 1781 December 5; A.L.S. 4p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Question of the Continental goods detained at Amsterdam for freight; surprised at Franklin's avowed intention of refusing payment of the bills; explanation of their part in the shipping of the goods; injustice of holding them responsible for miscarriage of plans; the honor of Congress concerned; danger of undermining the public faith in America and her cause.
  - to Van Arp and Co., 1781 December 5; A.L. 4p.; Neufville, John de, and Son. Amsterdam
    In reference to the cargoes which they shipped in the frigate of Mr. [Alexander] Gillon and which afterward was taken out and shipped on the "Aurora" and the "Liberty."
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781 December 6; D.S. Joseph Nourse, Register. 2p.; United States Treasury Warrant
    In favor of Captain De Freÿ of Pulaski's Legion.
  - to Princesse Sapieha., 1781 December 8; L. 2p.; Murinet, Comte de. Paris
    At her request made several efforts to learn something about M. [Thaddeus] Kosciuszko. Has now heard, through Chevalier de la Luzerne, that he is in good health. Several French officers who have returned say they saw the latter and that he was then with Gen. [Comte de] Grasse in Virginia; was employed as a military engineer. Is well thought of and enjoys consideration.
  - to ----- de St. Lambert, Paris, [1781?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Will be glad to see him and M. [St. Jean de] Crevecoeur; will await their visit.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [1781.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Warren, Winslow
    Called on Dr. Franklin with the intention of giving him an order on M. Grand for the fifteen guineas which he was so obliging as to lend him.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1781.]; Verses. 2p.; -----,-----
    Song composed at Amsterdam by a Frenchman on hearing of the captures made from Admiral Rodney's fleet by M. de La Motte Pi[c]quet on March 15th, 1781.
  - to ----- -----., Dr. of D. 1p.; -----,-----
    Certifying the signature of John Miller, a Justice of the Peace, of Philadelphia, on a deed to John S[c]haffer.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781; Dr. of D. 2p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Form of book for entry of bills of exchange.
  - to Abbé Arnoux, Paris., 1781; A.L.S. 1p.; Narduel, Abbé
    Regrets he is unable to accept Dr. Franklin's invitation. Requests Abbé Arnoux to present his regrets and explain the situation.
  - to [John] Adams., A.L.S. 2p.; Veuve Lalanne and fils
    Sending a packet, concerning the contents of which they beg Messrs. Adams and Franklin to confer and take suitable action.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, D. 3p.; Fennel, John
    Report on the loss of the English brigantine which was captured at sea by the privateer "Thomas" [of Salem Mass.], and afterwards wrecked on the coast of St. George, on of the Azores.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1781.]; Mme. 4p.; Fennel, John
    Report of a prize vessel taken from the English on the shipwreck of his vessel off the coast of the Azores.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781; Mem. 5p.; Bianchi, M. Paris
    Programme of lectures and experiments in physics, to be given at the Hotel Notre Dame in Paris.
  - to William Carmichael., [1785.]; L. 9p.; Caille, Etienne (Stephen) d'Audibert
    Thanks for requesting him to act as a correspondent for the United States in Morocco. Capture of an American vessel [brig "Betsy," of Philadelphia,] by a Moorish corsair; Captain James Erwin and his crew not maltreated but detained as captives at Mogador. Did all in his power to relieve their wants and be of service to them. The prisoners were grateful to him and showed their appreciation. The Emperor of Morocco is not inimical to the United States, but wishes to show that it is to their interest to seek his friendship and maintain diplomatic relations with him. The policy of the Moorish ruler towards all the Christian nations. He thinks the United States should not delay in accrediting a Consul or sending an Embassy to the Moorish sovereign to establish official relations and make a treaty or agreement with him, in order to protect and promote their commercial interests.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1781; 4p. 4to.; La Prise d'Yorck and de Glocester. Nantes
    Ode. Printed.
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.], Nantes., 1782 January 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Limozin, Andrew. Nantes
    In behalf of two American prisoners at Havre.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1782 February 18; D.S. 1p.; Courtauld, Samuel. Passy
  - to Jean-Hyacinthe de Magellan., 1782 March 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Nairne, Edward. London
    He and Dr. [Sir Charles] Blagden appointed by the Royal Society to go down and collect all the facts connected with the accident to the House of Industry; gives a detailed account of their observations.
  - to ----- -----., 1782 March 5; Dr. of L. 1p.; -----, -----. London
    Announcing the disgraceful news of the surrender of St. Christopher to Comte de Grasse.
    (In Italian.) [In Dr. Franklin's (?) hand-writing.]
  - to James Cuming., 1782 March 20; L.S. 1p.; Bright, Michael. Brest
    After he and four others made their escape from Forton Prison, and arrived at Havre de Grace, they were sent to Brest and put in the prison. Asks him to acquaint Dr. Franklin of their situation, that they may be released.
  - to Gerbier and Cie, of Nantes., 1782 March 20; D.S. [Marquis de] Castries. 1p.; The French Admiralty. Versailles
    Permits issued authorizing them to clear their Portuguese vessel "La Nostra Signora," loaded with provisions for San Domingo.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1782 March 23; D.S. Joseph Nourse, Register. 1p.; United States Treasury Certificate. Register's Office
    In favor of Baron d'Arendt for $2,997.37 bearing interest at 6 per cent. from March 18, 1782.
  - to King Louis XVI, of France and Navarre., 1782 May 20; A.L.S. John Hanson, Presid[en]t. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Congratulate him on the birth of a son. Hope his son will emulate his ancestors in adding to his titles the glorious appelation of protector of the rights of mankind. Also hope he will preserve the alliance between France and America.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1782. May ?]; Mem. 4p.; The British Cabinet
    The reply of the Court (of St. James) to a verbal suggestion of M. [Jean Mathias, Baron] de Simolin, made on April 29th, 1782, with reference to a termination of hostilities between England, France and Spain, and respecting efforts being exerted by the Austrian Court to bring about peace.
  - to Antoine Court de Gébelin., 1782 June 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Rabaut Saint-Etienne, Jean-Paul. Nimes
    Enclosing a letter (XXV, 781/2, see Vol. II, page 481) to be forwarded to Dr. Franklin; the writer, M. [Pierre] Saussine, requests Franklin's influence to procure the return to France of a young man called Boudon; reasons for his request.
  - to P. Penet., 1782 June 12; A.L.S. 8p.; Hooper, Stephen and Co. Newburyport
    Matters connected with the "Vengeance," and a reference to the new metal used for the bottom of ships. Sorrowful capture of the "Vengeance" as well as of the fine brig "Gates."
  - to Jonathan Williams, Jr., 1782 June 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Springer, Richmond. Brest
    Is a native of Rhode Island; was taken prisoner by the frigate "Recovery" and carried into Cork; sent from there to Kinsale; made his escape with five other Americans, took a boat and brought her into Brest; informed that if they sell their vessel before her condemnation, they will get but a small part of the profits; hears that M. [D'Albert de] Riou is one who takes advantage of strangers; begs him to write to Dr. Franklin and get their vessel condemned.
  - to ----- Grigson, Paris., 1782 June 18; A.L.S. 7p.; Johnston, A. Calais
    Obliged to work; chose that of instructing young ladies; anxious to settle in America under the protection of Congress, and be naturalized; would prefer South Carolina; if she cannot sail in September or October, desires a recommendation to a family in Paris who wish a governess; account of Miss Lambert; her education little improved since being in the convent.
  - to Tho[ma]s Aston Coffin, New York., 1782 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Brimmer, Martin. Boston
    Recommending Baron de la Marck [et Stein] and his daughter, who are embarking for Holland, in case their vessel should be taken and brought into New York.
  - to Ann Loviel (her daughter), Paris., 1782 July 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Evans, Ann. Gloucestertown, Va
    Horrified at the vile behavior of Mr. Loviel; sends her her marriage certificate (1p.) and a bill to pay her passage money to America.
    P.S. by James Anthony. Telling Mrs. Loviel of her mother's wretched state of health and begging her to hasten to Virginia. Enclosed letter, from Christiana Vaughan (1p.).
  - to Ann Loviel, Paris., 1782 July 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Christiana. Gloucester, Va
    Sorry to learn that she has been used so barbarously; always thought he was a deceiver. There are good things in store for her if she can get here. Her mother (Ann Evans) is left a widow again. She has sent the means to bring her [Ann Loviel] home. As for his denying his marriage there were enough witnesses at the wedding to certify to the truth of that. They all have been ruined by the British.
  - to Messrs. Poreau and Co., 1782 July 26; L.S. 1p.; Codner, Christopher. Greenwich Guard-ship, at the Nore
    Acknowledging the kindness shown them during their long confinement; their health very bad; Mr. Lambert is in a decline and cannot live long; if their is any money coming in, hopes that some will be sent them.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1782 July 26; D.S. 1p.; Vaux, Richard. Passy
  - to Ann Loviel., 1782; A.L.S. 2p.; Broomfield, Rosetta
    If she desires to see her mother [Mrs. Evans], she had better proceed home to Virginia immediately.
  - to Benjamin Vaughan, Paris., [1782. August 25.]; A.L.S. 3p.; Lisle, W
    Giving his opinion of the treatment used for [Benjamin] Franklin.
  - to M. Tascher, Paris., 1782 September 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Vidau fils, -----. Civita Vecchia
    Desires Dr. Franklin to obtain for him the position of Agent or Consul in one of the Italian ports.
  - to [John] Jay., 1782 September 30; L.S. 3p.; Barrett, Nathaniel. L'Orient
    Concerning the duty on a cargo of sugar.
  - to George Mason., 1782 September 30; L. 4p.; -----, -----. Virginia in Council
    Did not know Mr. P. Penet had any powers to borrow money on the credit of the State, till he received a letter from him complaining of Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin's refusing to authenticate his bonds; then he was immediately forbidden to act in any manner as Agent, and was ordered to send over a copy of his powers and instructions in order to a final settlement of his accounts. Thanks him for the steps he took to secure the ships and cargoes that were going to France. Hopes the destructive measure of foreign loans will be laid aside. Mr. [Philip] Mazzei's powers recalled. Instructed Mr. [Thomas] Barclay to forward the arms, etc., which the Ministry of France loaned to them, under convoy of some men-of-war. Concerning a contract made by Mr. Colougnac with Mr. Penet for tobacco.
  - to [Antoine François] Quètant., 1782 October 22; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple. Passy
    Regrets that his long absence from the United States prevents his being of service to his friend.
  - to l'Abbé [Poncelin] de la Roche-Tilhac., 1782 October 22; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple. Passy
    Sending the Almanae of Massachusetts and the Constitutions of each of the States.
  - to [Whom it May Concern]., 1782 October 28; A.D. 10p.; Belt, James
    Protest against the conduct and behavior of Chevalier de Quémy, Commander of the "Emeraude," frigate, a French vessel of 36 guns. Complains of the Commander for detaining and obliging him to wait with his ship and sail under a convoy, contrary to his desire and repeated remonstrances. An account of the Commodore's conduct while on the voyage, and his cowardly behavior in running away and leaving the ships "Matilda," "Jolly Tar," and others, to the mercy of the British frigate. An account of the "Matilda's" capture.
  - to Abbés de Chalut and Arnoux, 1782 October 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Sathonnay, Fay de
    Apologizes for being absent from Lyons during Sir [Edward] Newenham's stay there; any friend of Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin could not fail to be welcome.
  - to [Charles Joseph] Panckouche, Paris., 1782 November 12; L.S. 1p.; Anisson, ----- le fils
    Is very desirous to have Dr. Franklin's approval, but does not wish to show his press until it is entirely perfected.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1782 November 12; D.S. 3p.; Peyrimant, F. Edenton, N.C
    Depositions relative to Jean Wallier and Jean Jacques Wallier, natives of Switzerland who reside at Edenton, N.C., and to the death of the former in 1780.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1782 December 7; D.S. 1p.; Campbell, Lawrence Robert Captain in the British Army
    Parole.